Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts at the Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Says, 1857-1859; uva.00228; xxx.00417; xxx.00419; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 12.5 cm to 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  These manuscript lines were revised to form numbered section 5 of the ungrouped poem Says in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. Whitman cut four verse paragraphs in the 1867 Leaves of Grass version; from that point on the shortened poem appeared, ungrouped, under the title Suggestions until its final appearance in 1876.
- Says, 1857-1859; uva.00229; xxx.00417; xxx.00419; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 12.5 cm to 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  These manuscript lines were revised to form numbered section 6 of the ungrouped poem Says in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. Whitman cut four verse paragraphs in the 1867 Leaves of Grass version; from that point on the shortened poem appeared, ungrouped, under the title Suggestions until its final appearance in 1876.
- Says, 1857-1859; uva.00230; xxx.00417; xxx.00419; xxx.00413; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 12.5 cm to 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  These manuscript lines were revised to form numbered section 7 of the ungrouped poem Says in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. Whitman cut four verse paragraphs in the 1867 Leaves of Grass version; from that point on the shortened poem appeared, ungrouped, under the title Suggestions until its final appearance in 1876. The cancelled lines on the top section of the manuscript appear to be a draft of lines that were never published but that bear great resemblance to the various Thoughts and Thought (Of.. .) poems Whitman published throughout the many editions of Leaves of Grass.
- Nearing Departure, 1857-1859; uva.00231; xxx.00294; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 16 x 20 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Draft of a poem which Whitman titled Nearing Departure. Whitman retitled the poem To My Soul when it was first published, in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. In 1867 Whitman cut eight lines and revised others, retitling the poem As Nearing Departure and moving it to an untitled group of poems in the supplement Songs Before Parting. In 1872 it was finally retitled As the Time Draws Nigh and transferred to the cluster Songs of Parting within the main body of Leaves of Grass.
- So Long!, 1857-1859; uva.00232; xxx.00309; poetry handwritten 9 leaves 15 x 9 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Whitman numbered the leaves 75-81 in the upper right corner, with the exception of leaves 6 and 7, which are numbered at top center. In 1860 this was the final poem in Leaves of Grass; in 1867 Whitman cut twenty-one lines and transferred it to the end of the last Leaves of Grass supplement Songs of Parting. In 1872, with the transformation of this supplement into the cluster Songs Before Parting, it was permanently fixed as the final poem in the main body of Leaves of Grass.
- Sparkles from the Wheel, 1871; uva.00234; xxx.00244; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 25.5 x 20 cm (Folder 50-51)
  First published not in the 1860 Leaves of Grass, but in the separate publication Passage to India in 1871. Whitman penciled in the note "Long Primer / middling wide measure" in the upper left corner of the first leaf, and on the verso of the second wrote and deleted (also in pencil) the note "The worship of God is, honoring his gifts in other men, each according to his genius, & loving the greatest men best. Those who envy or calumniate great men, hate God William Blake[.]" After being bound with the rest of the Passage to India poems as a supplement to Leaves of Grass, in 1881 the poem was permanently transferred to the cluster Autumn Rivulets within the main body of Leaves of Grass.
- Fables, 1871; uva.00235; xxx.00496; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 23 x 20 cm (Folder 50-51)
  This poem became numbered verse paragraph 4 of section 2 of the title poem in the separate 1871 publication Passage to India. In 1881 the poem Passage to India was transferred, ungrouped, to the main body of Leaves of Grass.
- After death, about 1855; uva.00133; xxx.00623; xxx.00120; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 7 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Whitman apparently never used the recto lines, but the deleted lines on the verso bear a strong resemblance to the opening of his 1856 Poem of The Sayers of The Words of The Earth, titled in successive editions To the Sayers of Words (1860 and 1867), Carol of Words (1871, 1876), and, finally (in the 1881 edition of Leaves), A Song of the Rolling Earth. The undeleted ink line on the verso resembles a later draft of a line inscribed in Feinberg notebook #697 at the Library of Congress.
- [As to you], about 1855; uva.00134; xxx.00711; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 7 x 15.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  This section was evidently pasted to and then pulled away from another page; some fragments of that other page remain affixed to the top. Beneath them can be discerned the ink number 2. In the upper left corner appears an "X" within parentheses, which was formerly covered by the other page. Whitman apparently never used this poem or fragment.
- [Poem of], about 1855; uva.00006; xxx.00712; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4 x 8 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  These notes, on a very small scrap of paper, could have represented an early stage of a number of poems.
- A City Walk, about 1855; uva.00292; xxx.00085; xxx.00112; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4.5 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  A faint horizontal line beneath part of "A City Walk," along with the words' capitalization and central position on the page, indicate that Whitman may have contemplated using the words as the title of an independent poem. The closest he came to this title was City of Walks and Joys, the name he originally assigned to Calamus 18 in his Blue Book revisions of the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. This title was changed in the Blue Book to City of orgies, walks and joys and finally became City of Orgies in the 1867 edition. The manuscript also suggests making a list of things seen while "crossing the ferry" an idea later developed and published in the poem Crossing Brooklyn Ferry, 1860.
- Original. Walks Down This Street, about 1856; uva.00293; xxx.00085; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 7 x 16 cm paster to 4 x 15.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Both parts of the title are underlined. A wavy line appears at the foot of that section. The word "Original" at the head of the upper section suggests that Whitman was sketching out a new poem for a revised edition of Leaves of Grass. If it was the 1860 edition, as his style of inscription here appears to indicate, it is possible that this leaf could represent an early stage of the poem that would eventually become City of Orgies, 1867.
- Europe, about 1855; uva.00304; xxx.00110; xxx.00221; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 16 x 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  The recto notes represent an early stage of lines partially incorporated in Poem of Salutation, the new third poem in the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass, which was permanently retitled Salut au Monde! in the 1860 edition. If the note or title "Europe" suggests that Whitman might have first intended to divide his salutations into discrete sections based on the different continents, this is a plan he did not follow in the published version(s). The more polished (but deleted) lines on the verso represent a recasting in poetic form of several lines from the 1855 Preface. These were further revised for the 1856 Poem of Many in One, after which the first verse drafted on this page (cut off here, and beginning "over the Texan, Mexican, Florid[ian,]/ Cuban seas...") was dropped. The two verses below this, however, were preserved relatively unchanged through the poem's many transformations until the text was essentially fixed under the title By Blue Ontario's Shore in 1881.
- [And as the shores of the sea I live near and love are to me], about 1855; uva.00305; xxx.00110; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 13 x 14.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  These two verses represent a draft of lines that would be further revised and incorporated in the new 1856 poem Poem of Salutation, permanently retitled Salut au Monde! in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass.. A plate mark can be clearly seen on the verso.
- Poem of Pictures, about 1855; uva.00289; xxx.00110; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6.5 x 15.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  A phrase beginning "Picture of one of/ the Greek games" appears in the upper right corner, delimited from the rest of the notes with two curved lines. The words "Spanish bull fight" appear in their own semicircle (damaged by Whitman's cutting) in the lower right corner. The lines seem to occupy a middle space between the very early notebook poem Pictures and the 1856 Poem of Salutation (ultimately Salut au Monde!).
- [My two theses], about 1856; uva.00009; xxx.00713; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4 x 16 cm pasted to 10.5 x 16 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  On a small composite leaf of white wove paper, ruled in blue on one side, containing notes about developing two theses to "run through all the poems.. .."
- [The circus boy is riding in the], about 1855; uva.00010; xxx.00259; xxx.00110; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 10.5 x 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  The verso lines (beginning with the individually deleted line "O Walt Whitman, show us some pictures!" and continuing "America, always Pictorial!") represent a later draft of the beginning of the poem Pictures than the most complete extant version, which is contained in the pre-1855 Pictures notebook currently housed at Yale University. Critics have dated the lines to around 1880, when Whitman was working on a short version of Pictures both for magazine publication and for the 1881 edition of Leaves of Grass, where it was published as My Picture-Gallery. But Whitman's early style of inscription in this draft, along with the line "It is round—it has room for America, north and south" and his use of his own name in the deleted first line, all suggest that Whitman may have inscribed this draft around the same time that he was working on the new 1856 Poem of Salutations (eventually Salut au Monde!). This draft also suggests that at one point he may have considered linking what would become Poem of Salutations and the formally and thematically similar Pictures more directly. The lines on the recto, divided by a horizontal line, refer to images of a circus boy on a fleet horse and of watching those on a shore disappear. The relationship between either of these lines and Whitman's published works is unclear.
- [How can there be immortality], about 1855; uva.00014; xxx.00268; xxx.00048; xxx.00052; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4.5 x 14.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  These lines, appearing on a very small section of white laid paper cut and cropped irregularly, bear a strong resemblance to the (eventual) second verse paragraph in section 6 of Starting from Paumanok, first published in 1860 as Proto-Leaf. The fragmentary lines on the verso (beginning "Downward, buoyant, swif[t]"), represent a different version of a line incorporated in the pre-1855 notebook poem Pictures and of one inscribed in the 1854 notebook [I know a rich capitalist...], currently housed at the New York Public Library.
- [Pure water], about 1855; uva.00015; xxx.00714; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 16 x 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Below the trial verses, separated from them by a diagonal pencil stroke, appears a cartoon hand pointing to the annotation "I must have/ Poem[.]"
- [I am a student], about 1855; uva.00238; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 9.5 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The themes expressed in this early fragment would inform the lines that eventually became section 2 of Song of Myself; Whitman never used it verbatim. On the verso appears an undeleted but heavily revised early draft of famous lines, beginning "The spotted hawk swoops by...," incorporated in what would constitute the final canto of the poem in the 1867 and later editions of Leaves of Grass.-->
- [A little sum laid aside for burial money—a few clapboards around], about 1855; uva.00248; xxx.00526; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 17 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  This is a poetic rendition of a long sentence in the preface to the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. The prose sentence begins, "Beyond the independence of a little sum laid aside for burial-money, and of a few clapboards around..."
- [I subject all the teachings], about 1855; uva.00249; xxx.00111; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 15.5 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  These verses seem to have been part of a larger set of verses or poems. Because of the way the page is torn the final word could read "any," or it could just as easily read "an," indicating that a continuation of the lines has been lost. These lines prefigure section 6, especially beginning with the line "Here is the test of wisdom," of what would become Song of the Open Road, first published in 1856 as Poem of the Road.
- [I call back blunderers], about 1855; uva.00250; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4.5 x 19.5 cm pasted to 7 x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The first few lines were never used, but the last two verses (beginning "I offer men no painted saucers...") share similarities with the final verse paragraph (beginning "Stop this day and night with me and you shall possess the origin of all poems,") of what would eventually become section 2 of Song of Myself.
- [Do I not prove myself], about 1855; uva.00251; xxx.00048; xxx.00453; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 8 x 18.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  On the verso appear two undeleted lines beginning "Whatever I say of myself, you shall apply to yourself..." that eventually formed part of section 20 of Song of Myself. The deleted pencil lines beginning "I think there will never be any more heaven or hell / than there is now," were revised to form what would eventually become the second verse paragraph of section 3 of Song of Myself. After heavy revision the lines appearing on the recto of the manuscript were used in what would be section 41 of Song of Myself. These lines also bear relation to the untitled 14th poem of the Debris cluster ( 1860 ). The lines were not among the various passages of Debris that survived in the final poems of Leaves of Grass.
- [Never fails], about 1855; uva.00253; xxx.00011; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 14 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The lines, deleted with a single pencil stroke, appear after revision and expansion to have eventually formed part of section 21 of the cluster Calamus in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass; in the 1867 edition this section received the title That Music Always Round Me.
- [My hand will not hurt what it holds], about 1855; uva.00254; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 19 x 15.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The numbers 195 and 196 are inscribed on the verso and recto, respectively; these numbers, along with remnants of paste and binding tape along the left margin of the recto, suggest that the pages came from a notebook. The lines on the recto are deleted and appear to have been revised to form what is now section 28 of Song of Myself. The verso contains undeleted notes that begin with a list of animals and plants ("cottonwood—mulberry—/chickadee—large brown water-dog"), followed by a verse ("The suicide / went to a lonesome place...") that Whitman revised for use ("The suicide sprawls on the bloody floor of the bedroom,") in what would eventually constitute section 8 of Song of Myself. This verse is followed by another section of the natural "catalogue" ("locust, birch / cypress..."), below which appears a pair of verses (beginning "O dirt, you corpse—I reckon you are good manure—") used in what would be section 48 of the Song of Myself. The list of flora and fauna could anticipate any number of similar lists in Whitman, but bears the strongest resemblance to section 29 of Poem of Joys (final title: A Song of Joys), which first appeared in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- [I am a curse], about 1855; uva.00256; xxx.00048; xxx.00264; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 18.5 x 17.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  One leaf inscribed and revised on both sides in pencil. The trial lines on the verso (beginning "His very aches are exstasy") seem to have been revised for inclusion in what is now section 29 of Song of Myself. Whitman's unusual spelling of "ecstasy" indicates not only that the lines came very early in the process of writing Leaves of Grass, but that these lines may have originally been part of the proto-Song of Myself before being transferred to what would become The Sleepers. The verso lines and the words "I am a curse" link this leaf to two sections of draft verses in the earliest Library of Congress notebook (#80) beginning "Fierce wrestler!" and "I am a curse."
- [Black Lucifer was not dead], about 1855; uva.00257; xxx.00264; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 10.5 x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The deleted first line reads "I am a hell-name and a Curse..." The word "Sleepchaser's" appears in the upper right corner, perhaps indicating that Whitman was considering a title similar to the 1860 and 1867 title Sleep-Chasings even before the poem was first published in 1855, unless this is in fact a reworking of the section for the 1860 edition. The possibility of a post-1855 dating, however, appears to be slight given the similarities of paper choice and inscription techniques among other leaves and shared similarities to drafts in the earliest Library of Congress notebook. The poem Sleep-Chasings eventually became The Sleepers in 1871.
- [Topple down upon him], about 1855; uva.00258; xxx.00264; xxx.00271; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 15.5 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  This leaf, a reworking of the lines beginning "I am a Curse" in Library of Congress notebook #80, with verses added from the manuscript also in the University of Virgina collection that begins "I am a curse", appears to have come later in the revision process. The only line specifically linking the poem to the theme of slavery ("I look off the river with my bloodshot eyes, after / the steamboat that carries away my woman.—"), adapted from the "I am a curse" leaf, is deleted, and Whitman apparently rejected these lines and the "curse" theme in general as he moved toward the draft on the leaf in the Virgina collection that begins "I am a hell-name and a Curse...", which would eventuate in the 1855 published version. On the verso appear two sets of trial verses for what would eventually become the second verse paragraph of section 4 of the poem Faces, which in 1855 was published as the sixth of twelve poems in the first edition of Leaves of Grass.
- [The sores on my shoulders are from his], about 1855; uva.00260; xxx.00048; xxx.00264; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 8 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  Inscribed, revised, and deleted in pencil. On the verso appear the undeleted lines "Hear my fife! —I am a recruiter / Come, who will join my troop?" Scholars have recorded these lines as a version of the lines ("And now a merry recruiter passes, with fife and drum, seeking who will / join his troop...") in the pre-1855 notebook poem Pictures. The image of the musician recruiting attention equally for the problems of all connects these lines with section 18 of Song of Myself. Although the manuscript contains the phrase "iron necklace," which appears in the poem eventually titled To A Foil'd European Revolutionaire, the image of the steamboat carrying away the woman and the first person narrative style seem to connect this manuscript most clearly to the development of what would eventually become section 4 of The Sleepers first appearing in print with this title in 1871.
- [Where the little musk ox carries his], about 1855; uva.00261; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 6 x 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  Inscribed and revised on both sides in pencil. The only line used from the recto ("Where the life car is drawn on the slip-noose") is deleted here; it became part of what would eventually form section 33 of Song of Myself. The deleted verso lines (beginning "Who knows that I shall not myself / [...] time be a God, as pure and prodigious/ as any?") constitute a poetic revision of prose notes in Library of Congress notebook #85, and seem to have led up to what would eventually become section 48 of Song of Myself.
- [You there], about 1855; uva.00263; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 12.5 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The left side of the manuscript is torn as if the page had been removed from a notebook. This page was apparently inscribed very close to the publication of the 1855 Leaves of Grass; with a few revisions it became part of what would eventually be section 40 of Song of Myself. On the verso appear undeleted notes defining and illustrating such verse forms as "hexameters," "dactyl," "Spondee," "Iambus," and "Trochee." These notes represent an incomplete version of notes on a manuscript currently housed at Rutgers University. Scholars have commented that the Rutgers manuscript probably dates to 1856 or afterwards, when Whitman was pursuing a self-education in poetry, suggesting that the verso notes of this manuscript also date to that period.
- [And their voices], about 1855; uva.00264; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 4.5 x 19.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  A pencil question mark appears above a very faint line linking "valved" and "cornet." These half-prose, half-poetic notes were revised and incorporated in two separate verses of what would become Song of Myself: the eventual verse 597, in section 26 ("I hear...the keyed cornet") and verse 1067 in section 42 ("Ever the vexer's hoot! hoot! till we find where the sly one hides and bring him/ forth...").
- [The smell of the salt marsh], about 1855; uva.00265; xxx.00048; xxx.00226; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 8.5 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The first line originally read "Odor of the salt marsh, and of the mud and sea-weed[.]" An earlier version of these lines is also associated with proto-Song of Myself verses in Library of Congress Notebook #80 ("And the salt marsh and creek have/ delicious odors..."). The "unearthly laugh of the laughing-gull" reappears in what would eventually become line 763 (section 33) of Song of Myself. Most of the lines were incorporated, however (after further revision), into the tenth poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. This poem was titled Poem of The Child That Went Forth, and Always Goes Forth, Forever and Forever in the 1856 edition, after which it became number 9 in the 1860 group Leaves of Grass, number 1 of a different Leaves of Grass group in 1867, and, finally, There Was a Child Went Forth in the 1872 edition.
- [Children and maidens—strong men], about 1855; uva.00266; xxx.00715; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 7 x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)
  The laid paper was originally the last page of a letter; a few illegible words and part of a signature can be seen dimly through the back of the composite leaf. Whitman wrote his lines on the verso of the page after turning it sideways. These lines have no known relation to any published Whitman poem.
- [Full of wickedness], 1857-1859; uva.00267; xxx.00239; xxx.00066; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 15.5 x 8 cm (Box 1, Folder 88)